Finding Aid for John Panchuk papers, 1913-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Panchuk papers
1913-1981
Panchuk, John, 1904-1981.
85346 Aa 2 Ac
Battle Creek, Michigan, attorney. Oral history interview; materials relating to his involvement in Ukrainian-American organizations and activities.
3 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was begun by John Panchuk (donor no. 5143 ) and came to the library 1980-1985.
The collection is open to research.
John Panchuk was born April 4, 1904 in Gardenton, Manitoba to a pioneer Ukrainian family. He graduated from public schools in Detroit where his family had moved in 1916. He received his B.A. from the University of Michigan in 1926 and his law degree also from the U-M in 1928. He became a U.S. citizen in 1929.
Panchuk established a private law practice in Detroit in 1929. In 1937, he was named assistant state attorney general, and in 1941, he joined Federal Life and Casualty Co. as head of the legal department. In 1950, he was named secretary of the board of directors. He moved to Battle Creek in 1953 after the company moved its offices. At the time of his retirement in 1969, he had held the position of secretary and general counsel.
After World War II, Panchuk was appointed by Governor G. Mennen Williams to head the state commission for displaced persons and refugees. In this position, he was instrumental in finding homes for thousand of war refugees. Panchuk was an active member of the Democratic party, serving with the party's state central committee and heading up Calhoun County's Citizens for Kennedy Committee. Panchuk was a delegate to the 1960 Democratic National Convention that nominated John F. Kennedy for the presidency.
One of Panchuk's great interest was Eastern Europe studies, especially relating to the Ukraine. Both as an author and as a participant in various organization, Panchuk demonstrated an interest in the homeland of his parents. He wrote articles and gave speeches on the subject. His principal book was Schevchenko's Testament concerning the life and accomplishments of the 19th century Ukrainian poet-hero. Among the many organizations to which he belonged and served as president was the Ukrainian Youth League of North America, the Ukrainian Federation of Michigan, the Ukrainian American War Relief Committee, and the United Ukrainian American Relief Committee.
He died November 5, 1981.
The Panchuk includes an oral history interview and materials relating to his involvement in Ukrainian-American organizations and activities. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Chronological Materials; Associations/Organizational Activities and Interests; Political Activities and Interests; Ukrainian related materials; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Democratic National Convention (1960: Los Angeles); Michigan. Displaced Persons Commission.; Nazis.; Refugees--Michigan.; Shevchenko, Taras, 1814-1861.; Ukrainian Americans--Michigan.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Costumes--Ukrainian.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Families.; Funeral rites and ceremonies.; Panchuk, John, 1904-1981.; Panchuk family.; Ukrainian Americans--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Class of 1926.; University of Michigan. Law School. Class of 1928.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.StudentsSocial life and customs1921-1930.; University of Michigan. Spring Games--1924.1924.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Vita (Box 1)
  - Biographical clippings (Box 1)
  - Civic and professional honors (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder)
  - Oral history interview, October 26, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Panchuk family history: Descendants of Mihelo (Michael) Panchuk of Onut, Bukowina, Ukraine (1975); Bukowinian Settlements in Southern Manitoba Gardenton Area) (1971) (Box 1)
  - Panchuk/Panchuk family get-togethers, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Panchuk family: Michael Panchuk earlier personal documents (Box 1)
  - Publications (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of published articles and pamphlets (Box 1)
  - Retirement (Box 1)
  - Letters to the editor (Box 1)
  - Speeches by John Panchuk (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Chronological Materials
  (mainly clippings, printed material, with some correspondence and other dated items)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1913-1924 (Box 1)
  - 1925-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1942 (Box 1)
  - (undated), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - (undated), 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - (undated), 1950-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - 1977-1980 (Box 1)
- Associations/Organizational Activities and Interests
  - Detroit City Planning Commission, 1942-1945 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Commission on Displaced Persons and Refugees, 1949-1960 (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian-American Congress Committee, Initiative Committee
    - Chubety correspondence (Box 2)
    - Fik correspondence (Box 2)
    - Panchuk correspondence (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian American Federation of Michigan, testimonial banquet for Panchuk, April 27, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian-American Relief Committee, Initiative Committee, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Bandurists Chorus (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Congress Committee of America
    - "Rebirth and Reorganization of Ukrainian Congress Committee of America 1943-1944 Documentary Miscellany from the Archives of John Panchuk," 1943-1944 (Box 2)
    - "Three Decades of UCCA: 1940-1970" (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Graduates of Detroit and Windsor (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian National Association Lodge 146, premium payment book, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Professional Society of North America (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian War Relief and United Ukrainian American Relief Committee (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Youth League of North America, papers (clippings and published material), circa 1933-1975 (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Youth League Congress (meeting in Detroit August 31, 1935-September 1, 1935), registration book (with clippings, 1930-1940 re. Ukrainian associations) (Box 2)
  - YKKA, 1943 (Box 2)
- Political Activities and Interests
  - Presidential campaign, 1960
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Nationalities Division of Democratic National Committee (Box 2)
    - Michigan delegation to Democratic National Convention (Box 2)
    - Kennedy trip to Michigan (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 2)
- Ukrainian related materials
  - Taras Shevchenko statue, Washington, D.C. clippings, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Taras Shevchenko statue, Winnipeg, Canada, clippings (Box 2)
  - Printed material re. Ukraine and Ukrainians (Box 2)
  - Broadsides and posters re. Ukrainian activities, 1922-1932 (Box 2)
  - Translations from Ukranian by Panchuk (Box 2)
  - Letters from individuals in the Ukraine
    - Bhahun, Evherua (Box 3)
    - Bozyk, Olga (Box 3)
    - Briodok (Box 3)
    - Buryk, Ivan (Box 3)
    - Christmas greetings (various) (Box 3)
    - Hutzul, Lasia (Box 3)
    - Kommisar, Wasylyna (Box 3)
    - Lopatniuk, Domka (Box 3)
    - Mihayehuk, George (Box 3)
    - Myshuha (also newspaper clippings) (Box 3)
    - Oleynik, Domka (Box 3)
    - Onut distant relatives (Box 3)
    - Panchuk, Elpeaiphor; Cherninty: Buknnua and son Ivor (Box 3)
    - Panchuk, Hrytzko (Box 3)
    - Panchukjakuir (grandchildren and children of) (Box 3)
    - Permanent Mission of the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic to the United Nations (Box 3)
    - [school teacher acquaintance] (Box 3)
    - Tanaseyehuk, Stefan (Box 3)
    - Tihley, Lesia (including biography and publication), 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Tihley, Lesia (the mother of) (Box 3)
    - Turkerich, Wasyl (Box 3)
    - [visiting artists from the Ukraine] (Box 3)
    - Zozuliak, W (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous letters and other materials in Ukrainian, 7 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Letters from Waldemar Hunold, member of the Hitler Youth, to Florence Lightfoot, 1936-1937; photocopies (Box 3)
  - Loose items from scrapbook (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1918-1938 (Volume 1)
- Photographs
  - Ukrainians and Refugee Relief (Box 3)
  - Political Subjects (Box 3)
  - Ukrainian Family and Friends (USSR and Canada) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)